Guide to the O. Milton Gossett Papers, 1951-2004 and undated RL.00467
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
O. Milton Gossett papers
1951-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gossett, O. Milton (Oscar Milton), 1926-2006
RL.00467
14 Linear Feet
O. Milton Gossett was an advertising executive with Compton Advertising and Saatchi & Saatchi agencies. He was also a member of the National Advertising Review Board and conducted career workshops for college students in conjunction with the American Advertising Federation. The O. Milton Gossett Papers span the years 1951-2004 and document Gossett's advertising career with the Compton Advertising (Compton) and Saatchi & Saatchi agencies, along with materials relating to the merger of Compton with Saatchi & Saatchi in 1982, including correspondence with Charles and Maurice Saatchi. The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, writings and speeches, company newsletters, and other printed materials. Also included are advertising proofs and tear sheets, television commercial scripts and storyboards, videocassettes, scrapbooks, clippings, photographs, and cutouts of company employees, as well as artifacts and memorabilia. In addition, there is information on the history of the Procter & Gamble Company and its major advertising campaigns, including a number of advertisements for Ivory Soap.
2760 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Some materials pertaining to Saatchi & Saatchi are closed until 1 January 2011.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The O. Milton Gossett Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 2005 and 2007.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1925 May 27 Born Oscar Milton Gossett, New York, N.Y.
1943-1946 Officer, United States Naval Reserve
1944 Degree in mechanical engineering, Stevens Institute of Technology
1946-1947 Attended Columbia University
1947-1948 Attended Northwestern University Midshipman School
1949 Joined Compton Advertising
1949 May 29 Married Anna C. Scheid
1961 Vice President, Associate Creative Director, Compton Advertising
1968 President, Member of the Board of Directors, Compton Advertising
1975 Chief Executive Officer, Compton Advertising
1977 Chairman, Compton Advertising
1982 Chairman and Chief Executive Officer, Saatchi & Saatchi Compton Worldwide, upon the merger of Compton Communications and Saatchi & Saatchi
1998 Inducted into American Advertising Federation Hall of Fame
2001 Received the DeWitt Carter Reddick Award
2006 Mar. 1 Died, Mt. Kisco, N.Y.
Gossett was also a member of the National Advertising Review Board and conducted career workshops for college students in conjunction with the American Advertising Federation.
Collection Overview
The O. Milton Gossett Papers span the years 1951-2004 and document Gossett's advertising career with the Compton Advertising (Compton) and Saatchi & Saatchi agencies, along with materials relating to the merger of Compton with Saatchi & Saatchi in 1982, including correspondence with Charles and Maurice Saatchi. The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, writings and speeches, company newsletters, and other printed materials. Also included are advertising proofs and tear sheets, television commercial scripts and storyboards, videocassettes, scrapbooks, clippings, photographs, and cutouts of company employees, as well as artifacts and memorabilia. In addition, there is information on the history of the Procter & Gamble Company and its major advertising campaigns, including a number of advertisements for Ivory Soap.
The collection is organized into four series: Personal Files, Administrative Files, Writings and Speeches, and Audiovisual Materials. The Personal Files Series includes personal correspondence, photographs of Gossett and his colleagues, and items relating to Gossett's international travels. Other materials document Gossett's professional life, including early resumes. Also included is a daily diary from 1960-1961. The Administrative Files Series includes corporate publications, photographs, print advertisements, television commercial scripts, storyboards, speeches, subject files, and correspondence that document Gossett's career at Compton Advertising and Saatchi & Saatchi. The Writings and Speeches Series chiefly includes speeches, written and delivered by Gossett, relating to various advertising topics. Many speeches were created as part of Gossett's American Advertising Federation workshops, and were delivered at a number of colleges and universities. Writings include magazine articles written by Gossett, as well as an introduction to an article in the Encyclopedia of Advertising and Marketing. The Audiovisual Materials Series features twenty-seven videocassettes, primarily of television commercials produced by Saatchi & Saatchi.
Large-format print materials have been removed from their original series locations and relocated to Oversize Materials. Restricted materials have also been removed from their original series locations and relocated to Restricted Materials. Relocated items have been replaced in the Detailed Description of the Collection by dummy folders enclosed in brackets.
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in other Hartman Center collections, including the Bates Worldwide Inc. Records and the J. Walter Thompson Company Advertising Vertical File. For materials relating to Procter & Gamble, see also the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives, the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives--Account Files Collection; Domestic Advertising Collection; and Review Board Records--and the Sheldon Sosna Papers.
Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- United States; Consolidation and merger of corporations; Advertising executives -- History -- 20th century; Newsletters; Television advertising; Memorabilia; Photographs; Speeches; Scrapbooks; Scripts (documents); Cutouts; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- Soap; Advertising agencies; Proofs (printed matter); Clippings (information artifacts); Videocassettes; Tear sheets; Saatchi, Charles Nathan, 1943-; Saatchi & Saatchi; Saatchi, Maurice Nathan, 1946-; Compton Advertising, Inc.; Gossett, O. Milton (Oscar Milton), 1926-2006; Gossett, O. Milton (Oscar Milton), 1926-2006; Procter & Gamble Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Saatchi & Saatchi Compton Worldwide; Saatchi & Saatchi Advertising Worldwide
- Personal Files Series, 1951-1998 and undated, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes personal correspondence, approximately 80 photographs of Gossett and his colleagues, and items relating to Gossett's international travels. Other materials document Gossett's professional life, including early resumes. Also included is a daily diary from 1960-1961. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Biographical interview, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1994 and undated (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Financial materials, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, 1967-1973 and undated (Box 1)
  - O. Milton Gossett history, 1963-1998 and undated (Box 1)
    [Compiled by Gossett, with original folder title retained; contains an award ceremony program, clipping, magazine profile, and a good letter file, with correspondence dated 1988-1998.]
  - Philanthropy, 1995-1999 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Professional documentation, 1951-1992 (Box 1)
    [Includes early resumes and recommendation letter, recognition in Ad Daily, employment contracts, and business cards.]
- Administrative Files Series, 1952-2001 and undated (RESTRICTED), 6 boxes
  Materials document Gossett's advertising career at Compton Advertising and Saatchi & Saatchi. Company publications include Compton Digest, Compton People, and Saatchi & Saatchi's Perspectives, as well as a satirical newsletter about Saatchi & Saatchi entitled Eye Eye, and provide a glimpse into the corporate culture of these organizations. The series also features a set of 40 photographic cutouts of Compton employees that were used for client presentations. Although there is no contextual information regarding these figures available in this collection, there are several photographs in the Personal Files Series that feature Gossett surrounded by the figures. In addition, subject files primarily compiled by Gossett, as well as correspondence spanning from 1952-1998, provide background information on companies and colleagues. The series also includes a large body of advertising materials--print advertisements and television commercial scripts and storyboards--for clients including Black & White, Chase & Sanborn, El Producto, Kelly Tires, Knickerbocker Beer, Procter & Gamble, Socony Mobil Oil Company, and Tender Leaf Tea, among others. Ivory Soap is heavily represented through print advertisements, television commercial storyboards for the Ivory Girl campaign, as well as a New York City Department of Health campaign for AIDS awareness. Arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restrictions on access: Some materials pertaining to Saatchi & Saatchi are restricted until 1 January 2011. These materials have been physically removed to Restricted Materials, Box 6, and replaced by dummy folders enclosed in brackets.
  - Advertisements, 1951-1978 and undated (Box 1)
    - [Ivory Soap advertisements, 1951-1978 and undated, removed to Oversize Materials, Box 7] (Box 1)
    - [Portfolios (2) of Gossett's early advertising work, 1951-1966 and undated, removed to Oversize Materials, Boxes 8-9] (Box 1)
    - Television scripts and storyboards, 1953-1969 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1952-1998 and undated, 2 folders; 1 folder removed to Restricted Materials, Box 6 (Box 2)
  - [Cutout figures, removed to Oversize Materials, Boxes 10-11] (Box 2)
    [Consists of cutout images of Gossett's staff that were used for presentations.]
  - Printed materials, 1959-1993 and undated (Box 2)
    - [Advertising Age, 1968-1999, removed to Oversize Materials, Box 12] (Box 2)
    - Adweek, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Company publications, 1959-1995 and undated
      - Compton, 1959-1993 and undated, 8 folders; 1 folder removed to Oversize Materials, Box 12 (Box 2)
      - Saatchi & Saatchi, 1991-1995 and undated (Box 3)
    - Madison Avenue, 1969, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Speeches, 1967-1973
    [Speeches pertaining to administrative aspects of Compton Advertising. Other speeches are available in the Writings and Speeches Series]
    - Compton year-end sales meetings, 1967-1970, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Speech for Cincinnati's District and Sales Managers Meeting, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Speech topics by Compton personnel, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Subject files, 1958-2001 and undated
    - Compton, 1958-1983 (Box 3)
    - Internet, 1997-2001 (Box 3)
    - Procter & Gamble, 1979-2000 and undated (Box 3)
    - Saatchi & Saatchi, 1982-1999 and undated (Box 3)
    - [Saatchi, Charles, 1985-1995 and undated, removed to Restricted Materials, Box 6] (Box 3)
    - [Saatchi, Maurice, 1985-1991, removed to Restricted Materials, Box 6] (Box 3)
    - Wax, Ed, 1982-1988 (Box 3)
  - Workshop materials, 1991-2001 and undated (Box 3)
    [Career workshops conducted by Gossett in conjunction with the American Advertising Federation]
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1954-2001 and undated, 2 boxes
  Includes speeches, written and delivered by Gossett, relating to various advertising topics. Many speeches were created as part of Gossett's American Advertising Federation workshops, and were delivered at a number of colleges and universities. Writings include magazine articles written by Gossett, as well as an introduction to an article in the Encyclopedia of Advertising and Marketing. Preparatory materials such as notes and clippings accompany some of the items in this series. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Speeches, 1954-2001 and undated
    - Advertising Age creative workshop keynote speech, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Advertising Age presentation, 1990, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Advertising Age workshop speech, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Advertising Agency Minority Recruitment Conference (2nd annual), 1975 (Box 4)
    - Advertising Club of New York, speech to graduating class of Advertising and Marketing course, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Advertising Club seminar speech, The Tightened Belt, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Advertising Council, Un-selling Drug Mis-Use: A Total Communications Effort, 1973 (Box 4)
      [Speech written and delivered by Robert P. Keim, President, Advertising Council]
    - American Advertising Federation Annual Convention, Advertising's Eternal Verities, 1978 (Box 4)
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies, Institute of Advanced Studies, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Australian Magazine Publishers Association, Women: What Do They Want from Us Now? 1978 (Box 4)
    - Book Publishers speech, 1970 (Box 4)
    - College of William & Mary, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Direct Marketing Day speech, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Fisk University, 2001 (Box 4)
    - The Importance of Brands, undated (Box 4)
    - Ithaca College, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Ithaca (Cornell?), The Brief, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Ivory Bar speech material, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Lead-in anecdotes, undated (Box 4)
    - Magazine Publishers Association, Women: What Do They Want from Us, 1975 (Box 4)
    - McNeil University, Continuity of Advertising, or, How to Deal with 'More of the Same,' 1981 (Box 4)
    - National Center for Health Education, various speeches and talks, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Proprietary Association presentation, 1990, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Southern Methodist University (SMU), 2001 (Box 4)
    - Talk about Advertising, undated (Box 4)
    - Trinity College, 1991 (Box 4)
    - University of Missouri-Columbia School of Journalism, 2001 (Box 5)
    - University of Texas, 1995 (Box 5)
    - University of Texas, 2001 (Box 5)
    - University of Texas, DeWitt Carter Reddick Award, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
      [In addition to the speech, the folder contains correspondence between Gossett and the University of Texas, as well as a brief biographical note about Gossett.]
    - Writing Instrument Manufacturers speech, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Yale University School of Management, The Development of Advertising: Agency vs. Client, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous speeches and speech-related materials, 1954-1985 and undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Writings, 1971-1973 and undated
    - Advertising about Advertising campaign, Time magazine, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Encyclopedia of Advertising and Marketing materials, 1973 and undated (Box 5)
    - Questions that run through my mind when I hear that the recommended advertising budget is 'all in 30-second TV commercials, undated (Box 5)
    - Quotations from Chairman Gossett, undated (Box 5)
    - Selling the Client First, New York Times, 1973 (Box 5)
- Restricted Materials (Closed until 1 January 2011), 1 box
  - Administrative Files Series, 1985-1995 and undated (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
    - Saatchi, Charles, 1985-1995 and undated (Box 6)
    - Saatchi, Maurice, 1991-1995 and undated (Box 6)
- Oversize Materials, 6 boxes
  - Administrative Files Series, 1951-1999 and undated
    - Advertisements
      - Ivory Soap, 1951-1978 and undated (Box 7)
      - Portfolios of Gossett's early work, 1951-1966 and undated (Box 8-9)
    - Cutout figures, undated (Box 10-11)
    - Printed materials, 1951-1999 and undated (Box 12)
      - Advertising Age, 1968-1999 (Box 12)
      - Company publications--Compton, 1971-1972 (Box 12)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1975-2004 and undated (RESTRICTED), 4 boxes
  Videocassettes primarily feature Saatchi & Saatchi commercials. Also included is a video recording from an event celebrating Gossett's 35th anniversary with Compton; several photographs of this event are available in the Personal Files Series.
  Restrictions on access: Original videocassettes are closed to researchers. Use copies are available in the collection.
  - Original Recordings (CLOSED)
    - OR1. Gossett 35th Anniversary, 1984. Format: VHS. Use copy UC1 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR2. Original Saatchi, undated. Format: VHS. Use copy UC2 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR3. Saatchi 1982: 16 Spots, 1982. Format: VHS. Use copy UC3 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR4. Saatchi & Saatchi 2004, 2004. Format: VHS. Use copy UC4 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR5. Saatchi & Saatchi British Airways - Manhattan Landings, undated. Format: VHS. Use copy UC5 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR6. Saatchi & Saatchi Milt Gossett Advertising Hall of Fame, undated. Format: VHS. Use copy UC6 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR7. Saatchi & Saatchi New York Reel, November 2000, 2000. Format: VHS. Use copy UC7 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR8. Saatchi Classics Plus Italian Public Service Tuborg and Danone, 1992. Format: VHS. Use copy UC8 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR9. Saatchi Show Reel, undated. Format: Use copy UC9 in Box 16. Use copy UC in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR10. Old Reel: Garland-Compton, undated. Format: U-matic. No use copy available (preservation issues). (Box 13)
    - OR11. Saatchi/Compton merger, 1982. Format: VHS. Use copy UC10 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR12. Saatchi & Saatchi: Agency reel, including public service, 1995-1996. Format: VHS. Use copy UC10 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR13. Saatchi & Saatchi: Agency reel, January 2001. Format: VHS. Use copy UC10 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR14. Saatchi & Saatchi: Agency reel / Worldwide reel, 1998. Format: VHS. Use copy UC10 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR15. Saatchi & Saatchi: Business Communications: new business agency reel, July 1998. Format: VHS. Use copy UC10 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR16. Saatchi & Saatchi: Compilation reel, UK, January 1990. Format: VHS. Use copy UC11 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR17. Saatchi & Saatchi: Compilation reel, UK, September 1990. Format: VHS. Use copy UC11 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR18. Saatchi & Saatchi: International: Old Saatchi, Italy. Format: VHS. Use copy UC11 in Box 16. (Box 13)
      [This video is a duplicate copy of OR27]
    - OR19. Saatchi & Saatchi: International reel. Format: VHS. Use copy UC12 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR20. Saatchi & Saatchi: Original Saatchi. Format: VHS. Use copy UC11 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR21. Saatchi & Saatchi: Original Saatchi work: Thatcher material and show reel, 1975-1982. Format: VHS. Use copy UC13 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR22. Saatchi & Saatchi: Saatchi commercials, 1982. Format: U-matic. Use copy UC13 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR23. Saatchi & Saatchi: Saatchi reel, shown at Wake Forest, 2003-2004. Format: VHS. Use copy UC13 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR24. Saatchi & Saatchi: 'Shimmer' plus 10 good ones. Format: VHS. Use copy UC13 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR25. Saatchi & Saatchi: Staples Comm. Format: VHS. Use copy UC13 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR26. Saatchi & Saatchi Compton: New York City AIDS project/PSA, April 1987. Format: VHS. Use copy UC12 in Box 16. (Box 13)
    - OR27. University of Illinois, March 1992. Format: U-matic. Use copy UC12 in Box 16. (Box 13)
  - Preservation Masters (Not for Reference use)
    - MC1-MC8. Format: Betacam SP. Created: 2007-2008. (Box 14)
    - MC9-MC13. Format: Betacam SP. Created: 2007-2008. (Box 15)
  - Use Copies
    - UC1-UC13. Format: DVD. Created: 2007-2008 (Box 16)